（改编自艾萨克阿西莫夫的小说）
小时候 我告诉母亲
When I was a child, I told my mother
我想了解银河帝国里的每一颗行星
I wanted to learn every planet in the Galactic Empire…
从中心开始向外延伸 直到星之尽头
beginning in the center and moving out to Star's End.
每天晚上她都给我讲故事
Each night, she told me stories.
我穿越了无数光年
I traveled light-years…
（端点星）
我的心不断扩大 容下越来越多的世界
my mind expanding to hold more and more worlds.
但我从未到达端点星
But I never reached Terminus.
远离文明、荒无人烟的边缘地带
Straddling the farthest reaches of civilization, unsettled by man…
那里是帝国的尽头
it was the end.
我对那里的故事一无所知 直到许多年后
And its story remained dark to me until many years later.
直到它变成我的故事
Until it became my story.
直到它变成…
Until it became…
唯一的故事
the only story.
-别这样 -抱歉
-Don't do that. -Sorry.
-其他人呢  -我们在围栏和他们会合
-Where are the others? -We're meeting them at the fence.
我们有点迟
We're a bit late.
快点啊
Come on, guys.
-吉雅 -太多岩石了
-Gia! -It's so rocky.
完了
Shit.
主教爪
A bishop's claw.
-在上谷附近 -我们得小声点
-Up-valley. -We need to be real quiet.
空域从那边开始 靠近那块岩石
The null field starts all the way up there. Near that rock.
人们称之为“穹窿”
They called it "the Vault."
所有殖民者都很清楚
All the colonists knew for certain
它在周围投射了一个阻止人们靠近的力场
was that it projected a field designed to keep people away.
没有人能突破
No one could breach it.
好吧 你先去
Right, you gonna go first?
不是你先吗
I thought you were first?
如果你先去 到达岩石后面 放下你的标记
You go first and put your marker past the rock,
-我就让你碰我的一边胸部 -吉雅
-I'll let you touch my tit. -Gia.
一分钟
For one minute.
十秒
Ten seconds.
或者你可以看两边胸部 看30秒
Or you can look at 'em both for 30.
你向月亮发誓
Swear on your moon.
庄严发誓
Four-sworn.
-你赢了也得不到好处 -我能看到他尿裤子
-You get nothing if you win. -Get to watch him piss his pants.
他不可能成功
He isn't gonna make it.
加油 凯尔
Come on, Keir.
凯尔
Keir.
你还好吗
Are you okay?
-你弟弟是个废物爪子 -吉雅 别笑他了
-Your brother is an assclaw. -Gia, stop laughing at him.
-他真可悲 -我差点就到了 我很接近了
-He's pathetic. -I was almost there. I was close.
波利 你要去哪
Poly, where you going?
-该死 波利 -波利 回来
-Shit. Poly! -Poly, come back!
-我们没做交易 -我知道
-We don't have a deal. -I know.
我想见幽灵
I wanna see the ghost.
好的
Okay.
该死
Shit.
-波利 -他不动了
-Poly? -He's not moving.
波利
Poly?
-我们得去找帮手 -那你干嘛站着不动
-We gotta get help. -What you standing there for then?
他们都走了 吃吧
They're all gone. Eat.
我看见幽灵了
I saw the ghost.
你看见的是我
You saw me.
吃吧
Eat.
你应该转身回去 像你的朋友凯尔一样
You should've turned back, like your boy Keir.
有人因试图接近那里而受伤 真的
People who've tried to get closer have been hurt. Really.
你没有
You weren't.
你保持着纪录 但你没事
You got the record and you're okay.
是吗
Am I?
你的标记那么远 从没有人见过它
Your mark is so far, no one's ever seen it.
那是因为它不存在 幽灵也不存在
That's because it doesn't exist. And neither does the ghost.
守卫者 你觉得它什么时候 会向我们展示它的身份
When do you think it's going to tell us what it is, Warden?
你可以叫我塞佛
Call me Salvor.
你认为它在乎我们
And you assume it cares anything about us?
它才不在乎
It doesn't.
无法接近它的不只有人类 任何生物都不行 鸟、昆虫
It's not just people it keeps away. It's everything. It's birds, insects.
从来没有人突破空域 以后也不会有
No one's ever gotten through the null field, and no one ever will.
它警告我们远离 所以别冒险
It's warning us to stay away. So stop tempting fate.
走吧 路上小心
Go. Be careful.
-那边有一只主教爪… -在上谷 我知道
-There's a bishop's claw-- -Up-valley. I know.
塞佛哈定、候伯马洛、骡
Salvor Hardin. Hober Mallow. The Mule.
（川陀）
有一天我将认识这些名字
I would learn these names one day.
（35年前）
为了拯救人类而抗争的英雄和恶徒
The heroes and villains fighting for the salvation of mankind.
但是要想了解我们的未来
But to understand our future,
我们必须铭记过去和那些创造历史的人
we have to remember the past and the ones who caused it all.
一位数学家
A mathematician.
一位殉道者
A martyr.
一位谋杀犯
A murderer.
还有最重要的人物 哈里谢顿
And the most important player of all, Hari Seldon.
她很快就会上路
She'll be on her way soon.
一切都会好起来的 瑞驰
It will all work out, Raych.
一切都在消亡
Everything is dying.
那不意味着最后不会好起来
That doesn't mean it won't all work out.
你是否曾希望有其他的方式
Do you ever wish there was another way?
每天都希望 孩子
Every day, son.
但现在是最佳时机
But this is the optimal time.
（辛纳克斯）
86960947
86,960,947.
86960957
86,960,957.
86960971
86,960,971.
-86960987 -时间到了
-86,960,987-- -It's time.
盖尔 你准备好了吗
Gaal? Are you ready?
是
Yes.
我一辈子都向外眺望 梦想着自己生活在别处
All my life, I looked out and dreamed of being somewhere else.
现在我意识到我会有多想念眼前的景色
Now I realize how much I'll miss this view.
我必须牢牢记住这个画面
I have to remember it perfectly.
不 你不必这样
No, you don't.
我们可以向先知祭司们呈请
We can petition the Seer priests.
现在止步还不迟 现在决定留下还不迟
It's not too late for you to stop this. It's not too late for you to stay.
不
No.
这里已经容不下我了 妈妈
There's no place for me here anymore, Mom.
如果留下 我会死去
I'll die if I stay here.
但是我在川陀将是安全的
But on Trantor, I'll be safe.
被人所接纳
Accepted.
昂起你的头
Hold your head high.
就是她
That's her.
他们都憎恨我 你不恨我吧
They all hate me. You don't hate me, do you?
绝对不会 盖尔 我永远都爱你
Never, Gaal. I'll always love you.
你是我人生最大的喜悦
My greatest joy.
跟我来吧
Come with me.
我们在外面会迷失自己的
We'd be lost out there.
去吧
Go.
我爱你
I love you.
去吧 孩子
Go, child.
转移指令启动
Beginning transfer sequence.
请移动至跃迁舱 准备上路
Please move to jumppods and secure for travel.
你说了什么话吗
Did you say something?
没有 但我本想问你 这是不是你第一次搭乘帝国跃迁舰
No. But I was going to ask if this was your first time on an imperial jumpship.
对 是的 我有点紧张
Yes. It is. I'm a bit nervous.
把手放在屏幕上就可以了
Just place your hand on the screen.
-它会扫描你的参数 -谢谢
-And it will scan your metrics. -Thank you.
-杰瑞尔 -盖尔
-Jerril. -Gaal.
辛纳克斯人
Synnax?
听得出你有一点口音
Picked up just a hint of it in your accent.
在核心区很少听到这种口音
You don't hear it much at the Core,
但我有时会去银河系边缘的世界
but I travel near the rim worlds sometimes.
看得出把祷告石移除的那个人技术很好
Whoever took the prayer stones out did a great job.
如果不仔细看都看不到疤痕
You wouldn't see the scars if you didn't know to look.
抱歉 我太无礼了
Sorry if I overstepped.
我不受影响
It doesn't screw me up,
但有些人在跃迁之后会有宿醉感
but some people come out of the jump feeling a little hungover.
我不喝酒
I don't drink.
我的父母从前常常潜水采海藻 所以我们很早就起床
My parents dove an algae farm, and we woke up pretty early.
他们会确保你全程保持睡眠状态
You're gonna sleep through this. They make sure of it.
在跃迁期间 他们不能启动重力 我不知道为什么
They can't have the grav on during the jump. I don't know why.
重力产生器输出的引力波
Well, the grav generators output a waveform
会削弱跃迁驱动器
that corrupts the jumpdrive's ability
在跨维度速度下标绘四维节点的能力
to plot fourth-dimensional points at transdimensional speeds.
你为什么去川陀
Why are you going to Trantor?
我将与哈里谢顿共事
I'm going to work with Hari Seldon.
我赢得了一场数学竞赛
I won a math contest.
哇 哈里谢顿 而且你来自辛纳克斯
Wow. Hari Seldon. And you from Synnax.
那是个很大型的竞赛
It was a pretty big contest.
开始跃迁 三、二、一
Commencing jump in three, two, one.
你怎么会醒来
How are you awake?
我们在跃迁期间全程沉睡 真可惜
It's a pity we have to sleep through the jump.
据说外面的光很美
It's supposed to be quite the light show.
但如果你不是太空人
But if you're not a Spacer,
你的身体和大脑可能无法保持一致
you can find your body and mind taking different trips.
我从头睡到尾
I slept through the whole thing.
旅程即将结束 请准备
…and prepare to disembark.
哇
Wow.
如果说帝国有哪方面在行 那就是建筑
If the Empire is good for anything, they can damn well build.
真壮观
This is incredible.
欢迎来到川陀 帝国中心
Welcome to Trantor, the eye of the Empire.
请心怀尊敬 享受和平
Please respect and enjoy the peace.
他们是士兵吗
Are those soldiers?
在你的世界大概不算新闻
Probably didn't make the news on your world,
但银河边缘地带发生了一些冲突
some sort of kerfuffle at the galaxy's edge,
安纳克里昂和狄斯比斯
Anacreon and Thespis.
帝国评鉴师在交火过程中受牵连了 所以现在这成了一件大事
Imperial appraisers got caught in the cross fire, so now it's a big deal.
保证人和联络方式
Sponsor and contact?
哈里谢顿博士 斯璀璘大学
Dr. Hari Seldon. Streeling University.
返回母星时间
Expected return to home planet?
我不会回去 这里是我的家了
I'm not going back. This is my home now.
你可搭乘轨道上的任意车厢 请心怀尊敬 享受和平
Any car on the stalk. Please respect and enjoy the peace.
谢谢
Thank you.
现在我对你有了一点了解
Now that I know you a little better,
我就不浪费口舌为你解释一切了
I won't waste my breath explaining everything.
但接下来很棒
This part is great though.
请前往任何可用车厢
Please make your way to any available car.
本车厢即将开始沿着轨道下降
This car will commence its descent down the stalk momentarily.
我会一直保持清醒
I'm gonna stay awake the whole ride.
我也是
Me too.
从川陀站下降至星球地表需要14个小时
It takes 14 hours to drop from Trantor Station to the planet's surface.
不过严格说来那不是地表
Although, technically, it's not the surface.
数十亿的居民在川陀外层之下居住
Billions of citizens spend their lives beneath Trantor's outer shell,
在地底下100层忙碌一辈子
toiling away on a hundred subterranean levels
从来都见不到太阳或星星
without ever seeing the sun or the stars.
自然世界仅存的一切都属于帝王们
Whatever remained of the natural world belonged to the Emperors.
黎明
Dawn.
白昼
Day.
黄昏
Dusk.
一脉相承的王朝
The Genetic Dynasty.
处于不同年纪的克里昂一世克隆人
Clones of Cleon I, decanted at different ages.
欧里奥师傅
Master Orlio.
大帝
Empire.
你为我们工作多少年了
How long have you worked for us?
我为大帝工作已有68年
Sixty-eight privileged years, Empire.
从12岁开始清理壁画时起
Started cleaning the Mural when I was 12.
至今已经从一端到另一端清理了四次
Gone from one end to the other four times over since then.
每一个颜色已经熟记在心了
Know every grain of chroma by heart now.
告诉我 有些颜色是否更难清洁
Tell me, are there some colors more resistant to cleaning than others?
紫红色
Plum.
长春花色
Periwinkle.
藏红色尤其棘手
Saffron is a particularly truculent pigment.
血红色呢 是不是也棘手
What about crimson? Is crimson truculent?
大帝
Empire?
我们得知
It's come to our attention
在你的居所发现了哈里谢顿著的文章
that a tract authored by Hari Seldon was discovered in your quarters.
对不起 大帝 是我愚钝
Apologies, Empire. It was foolish of me.
我只是…
It's just that I'd--
听人提到他的主张 感到好奇
Heard whispers of his proclamations and were curious.
人们把谢顿称为“乌鸦嘴” 是吗
They refer to Seldon as "the Raven," don't they?
我听说他对帝国有不少批评
I hear he's rather critical of the Imperium.
我很高兴地向您报告 他的文字都是毫无根据的垃圾
Well, I'm happy to report that his words are baseless trash,
我再补充一点 用词狂妄
and atrociously written, if I might add.
尽管如此 这个男人已聚集了一帮信众
Nevertheless, the man has amassed a following.
他们把希望寄托在 乌鸦嘴谢顿说的每个字词上
People who hinge their hopes on every word Raven Seldon utters.
言语是星星之火 可以燎原 欧里奥
Words have a way of fanning into wildfires, Orlio.
我忠诚不二 大帝 我绝不会…
I am loyal, Empire. I would never--
我知道你不会 所以我才亲自找你谈论这件事
I know you won't, which is why I broached this subject in person.
大帝
Empire--
黎明兄弟 你今早学了什么
What are your lessons this morning, Brother Dawn?
外围星域的王国
The Outer Reach kingdoms.
我学会了一首安纳克里昂的古老歌曲 是关于狩猎的
I learned an old Anacreon song about hunting.
音乐中往往藏着真理
Well, there is much truth in music.
一个男孩用刀划开小鹿的皮肉 将它的身体作为庇护所
A boy bleeds a fawn with a knife and then takes shelter in her coat.
那一首并不是狩猎歌
That one's not really a hunting song.
那是一首淫曲 唱的是男孩与女人的初夜
That's a dirty song about a boy's first time with a woman.
在你脑中再唱一次 别把两者混淆了
Play it back in your mind. And don't confuse the two.
白昼兄弟 请把孔雀留给厨师处理
Brother Day, please leave the peacock to the cooks.
就算你不亲自动手 你的自传也仍然会很有趣
You'll be no less fascinating to your biographers.
黄昏兄弟认为我这么做 是为了让自己更有吸引力
Brother Dusk imagines I do this to be colorful.
白昼兄弟总是曲解我的话 却不曲解禽肉
And Brother Day puts more words in my mouth than he does poultry.
是猪油
It's the lard.
厨师在烤肉之前用针把猪油注入皮下
The cooks inject it under the skin with a needle right before roasting.
-知道为什么他们用针吗  -因为更高效
-Do you know why they use a needle? -Because it's efficient?
因为他们担心如果用刀
Because they're afraid if they use a knife,
这种传统的方式
as is the time-honored way,
他们可能会划破孔雀皮 那我就会把他们送到50层下的炖肉锅里去
they might rip the skin, and I'll send them to a stew-pot stall 50 levels down.
这确实是个大问题 为什么
All of which is a problem. Why?
因为当人们担心自己做好本职时
Because when people are afraid to do their job right,
他们一定会出错
they're certain to do it wrong.
-这叫管理不当 -这叫烤得不当的孔雀
-That's poor stewardship. -It's poor roast peacock.
不是每一件事都可以总结出道理
Not everything is a teachable moment.
大帝
Empire.
德默泽尔
Demerzel.
狄斯比斯和安纳克里昂的使团即将到达
The delegations from Thespis and Anacreon are arriving.
-他们看起来如何  -脾气暴躁
-How did they seem? -Peevish.
一帮蛮族 麻烦很多 价值很少
Barbarian kingdoms. They're more trouble than they're worth.
让外围星域贸易局 把关税预测资料带到寝宫
Have Outer Reach Trade bring tariff projections to the residence.
穿得体面些 让人为你梳理头发
Dress nice. Have someone brush your hair.
这不是我们本周最重要的事
It's not the most important thing we'll do this week,
但却是他们这辈子最重要的一件事
but it's the most important thing they'll do in their lifetime.
安纳克里昂和狄斯比斯 观察两方的举止
Anacreon and Thespis. Observe the mannerisms of each party.
他们憎恨对方
They hate each other.
他们是不共戴天的仇敌 但战争的代价高昂
Their enmity is legendary. But war is expensive.
所以我们召他们过来加以谴责 令双方达成和解
And so we have called them onto the carpet to broker a peace.
多谢你的陪伴
Thanks for the company.
祝你的新工作一切顺利 希望哈里谢顿值得你这么远来到这里
Good luck with the new job. I hope Hari Seldon is worth the trip.
谢谢
Thanks.
挺帅的
Cute.
瑞驰…你在哪里
Raych, Raych, Raych. Where are you?
-那就是我 -什么
-That's me. -What?
是我 瑞驰
That's me, Raych.
我在哈里手下做事 谢顿博士
I work for Hari. Dr. Seldon.
-行李领取处在这边 -不用了
-Baggage Claim is this way. -No.
不 我的行李都在这
No. This is all I have.
好吧
Okay.
请跟我来 参观本星球其他地方吧
Then the rest of planet is this way.
据说是完美的复制品
It's supposed to be a perfect replica.
虽然我们在地下的人不会知道
Not that we'd know under the outer shell.
64层的一半区域 都是服务器投放的天空影像
Half of level 64 is just servers running skies.
川陀这里还有先知教堂吗
Is there still a Seer church here on Trantor?
那下面应该有 在22层
Down there, I think. Level 22.
我想看看
I'd like to see it.
怎么
What?
抱歉 我…
Sorry, I've--
我从没见过来自辛纳克斯的人
I've never met anyone from Synnax before.
展现共情与管理精神
An expression of compassion and stewardship,
这是魂之壁画
the Mural of Souls,
每日都由一脉相承的王朝资深人员打理
worked on every day by the senior member of the Genetic Dynasty.
壁画描绘了四个世纪的和平和银行家族
The Mural depicts the four-century age of peace and the Galactic Family.
注意到动态的颜色吗 色彩轻微地移动
Notice the active chroma? How the pigment subtly moves?
星省使者赞登
Provincial Ambassador Xandem.
你对壁画有什么问题或评论吗
Do you have a question or a comment about the Mural?
我们只是在感叹帝国的仁爱之心
We were just marveling at the Empire's benevolent reach.
因为确实令人惊叹
For it is a marvel.
86963537
86,963,537.
86963549
86,963,549.
86963563
86,963,563.
963,567.
86963573
86,963,573…
-你在祈祷吗  -不是 为什么这么问
-Are you praying? -No. Why?
你的嘴唇在动
Your lips were moving.
是 我感到紧张时会数质数
Yeah. When I'm nervous, I count primes.
哈里说你会想看这个的
Hari said you'd wanna see this.
盖尔 这位是哈里
Gaal, meet Hari.
谢顿博士
Dr. Seldon.
你邀请我来这里 我感到很荣幸
I am so honored you invited me here.
你觉得帝国图书馆如何
What did you think of the Imperial Library?
太惊人了 这么多书在一个地方
It's amazing. So many books in one place.
我猜在辛纳克斯很难找到书
I imagine books were hard to come by on Synnax.
请坐
Please, sit.
你知道卡里的第九条折叠定理证明吗
So, you know Kalle's Ninth Proof of Folding?
是 如果没有它 我不可能解出亚布拉克萨斯猜想
Yes, I couldn't have solved Abraxas without it.
其他人都没想到使用这条证明 500年来从未有人这么做过
No one else thought to use it. Not in 500 years.
你认为原因是什么
Why do you think that is?
卡里的文字充满诗意
Kalle's writing is poetic.
很美 但是很难想象其内容严谨
It's beautiful, but it's hard to imagine there's any rigor there.
所以学者们不会读她的作品
So serious scholars don't read her.
你为什么读呢
Why did you?
我最初读卡里的作品 是为了寻找她文字中的韵律
I went to Kalle for the rhythm of the words at first.
我没有注意到数学的部分
I missed the math.
但当我体会文字背后的意义
But when I read between the lines,
我意识到她提出了一个激进的理论
I realized she was proposing a radical theory
是关于非阿基米德局部域的整数环
about rings of integers in non-Archimedean local fields.
确实如此
Indeed she was.
但我很好奇
It does make me wonder, though,
你一开始是如何 发现卡里的第九条证明的
how you've managed to stumble across Kalle's Ninth Proof in the first place,
考虑到你身处的地方
given where you were.
这里不是辛纳克斯 盖尔 在这里 好奇心不是一种罪
This isn't Synnax, Gaal. Curiosity isn't a crime here.
我很孤独
I was lonely.
那里几乎没有人像我一样思考
Almost no one there thought like I thought.
但是数学不看立场 不会品头论足
But math doesn't take sides. It doesn't judge.
你这样聪明 在那样一个地方一定感到孤独
I imagine you were lonely, a mind like yours in a place like that.
这是卡里的证明原稿 以她的母语特莱克斯语写的
Kalle's original proof manuscript. Written in her native Thraxian.
明天他们会逮捕我和你
They're going to arrest me tomorrow. And you.
-什么  -几乎已经确定
-What? -It's almost a certainty.
逮捕 为什么
Arrest? Why?
不会发生的概率非零 但那个数字小得不值得讨论
There's a nonzero chance it won't happen. But it's not a number worth discussing.
不…这一定是哪里出了错
No. This has to be a mistake.
人会说谎 盖尔 数字不会
People lie, Gaal. Numbers don't.
你熟悉我在心理历史学方面的研究
Are you familiar with my work? Psychohistory?
-每个数学家都读过你的… -你认同那个概念吗
-Every mathematician has read your-- -Do you agree with the concept?
理论上是 但我不知道这和…
In theory. But I don't know what it has to do with--
这不是理论
It's not a theory.
那是以数字形式表现的人类命运
It's the destiny of the human race expressed in numbers.
那也是帝国将逮捕我们的原因
And it's the reason the Empire will take us.
他们担心你能预知未来
They're worried you can predict the future.
他们担心人们相信我能预知未来 他们不喜欢我所预知的未来
They're worried people believe I can. And they don't like the future I predict.
那未来是什么
Which is what?
川陀将被摧毁 帝国将灭亡
Trantor is going to be destroyed. The Empire will fall.
你应该明白 这些并不是我急于想告诉人们的事情
You understand, these aren't things I'm anxious to tell people.
这只是数学告诉我的事
It's just what the math tells me.
为什么让我大老远过来 只为了逮捕我
Why let me come all this way just to arrest me?
这是个好问题 你告诉我答案吧
That's a good question. You tell me.
因为我解出了亚布拉克萨斯猜想
Because I solved Abraxas.
他们认为只有我能证明你是错的
They think I'm the only one who can prove you wrong.
确实只有你能证明我错了 但我没有错
And you are, if I was. But I'm not.
你带我观光时知道这一切吗
Did you know all this when you were showing me the sights?
事关重大 远比你想象得复杂 盖尔
There's more at stake here than you can imagine, Gaal.
我冒着生命危险来到这里
I risked my life coming here.
现在你希望我再冒一次险 只为了支持你的计算结果
And now you want me to risk it again just to support your numbers?
你说得不完全准确 对吧 盖尔
That's not entirely accurate, is it, Gaal?
你离开辛纳克斯也是为了不被逮捕
You left Synnax one step ahead of arrest yourself.
所以你知道数学从来都不只是数字
So you know math is never just numbers.
被错的人掌握 它会变成武器
In the wrong hands, it's a weapon.
被对的人掌握 就是解放
In the right hands, deliverance.
去吧
Go.
休息一下
Get some sleep.
他们应该会用大半个晚上定位你的酒店
It should take them most of the night to divine your hotel.
我们很快会再见面的
We'll talk soon.
我知道你来这里不是为了这个奖品
I know it's not the prize you came here for…
但目前只能送你这个了
but it will have to do.
-我不能收下 -当然能
-I can't keep this. -Of course you can.
这栋建筑总有一天会烧成灰烬 偷走它是慈悲之举
This building will burn one day. Stealing is a mercy.
我读过他的所有心理历史学研究
I've read all his work, psychohistory.
我从没想过他会以这种方式应用
I just never imagined he'd use it this way.
帝国不会伤害你的 他们需要你
The Empire isn't gonna hurt you. They need you.
你并不确定这一点 他也是
You don't know that. And neither does he.
-盖尔 -不
-Gaal-- -No.
你没见过
You haven't seen it.
如果一个星球要你死 你一定会死
When a planet wants you dead, you die.
外围星域安纳克里昂星 使者赞登
Ambassador Xandem, Planet Anacreon, Outer Reach.
大帝
Empire.
以塔林森林最古老的树木雕刻而成
Carved from the oldest tree in the Tallyn Forest.
同一块木材也用于雕刻
The same wood used to carve the bow
安纳克里昂最伟大的猎手拉肯柯恩的弓
of Anacreon's greatest hunter, Larken Keaen.
谢谢你 使者
Thank you, Ambassador.
你喜欢魂之壁画吗
Did you enjoy the Mural of Souls?
是 大帝 我从未见过这样的壁画
Yes, Empire. I have never seen anything like it.
外围星域狄斯比斯星 荣誉外交官舍恩舍
Honored Diplomat Shae Un Shae, Planet Thespis, Outer Reach.
大帝
Empire.
狄斯比斯之《洗礼经》
A Thespin Book of Ablution.
上面的金属丝饰是最近新锻造的 为了向帝国的和平致敬
The filigree was recently smithed to honor the imperial peace.
谢谢你 荣誉外交官
Thank you, Honored Diplomat.
谢谢两个使团来到川陀
And thank you, both delegations, for making the journey to Trantor.
虽然你们别无选择
Not that you had a choice.
九个世纪以来 安铎星带协议 为你们的星球带来和平
For nine centuries, the Anthor Belt Agreement served your planets well.
去年 狄斯比斯发现了一颗异常小行星
Last year, Thespis identified a rogue asteroid,
他们认为它从协议规管的区域漂移至区外
which they believe drifted from the area governed by the agreement.
我们没有正式的立场
We took no official position.
只表达我们一成的意见
Just our 10%.
安纳克里昂认为狄斯比斯的举动有违协议
Anacreon believes Thespis acts in bad faith.
帝国认为帝国的臣民的血
The Empire believes imperial blood has been shed
已洒在离家五万光年的一块冷岩上
on a cold rock 50,000 light-years from home.
这三种想法中的任何一种 都曾引致上千次战争
For any of these three beliefs, a thousand wars have been fought.
接下来的几天我们将判定 是否将有另一场战争
The next days will determine if there will be another.
心怀尊敬 享受和平
Respect and enjoy the peace.
黎明兄弟 你的想法是什么
Brother Dawn, what do you make of that?
狄斯比斯人想提醒你
The Thespins want to remind you
安铎星带小行星对他们的信仰有多重要
how important the Anthor Belt asteroids are to their religion.
但看这个金属丝饰
But look there. In the metal filigree.
这个徽章的图案是以重金属钯制成的
The pattern in the sigil is made of heavy palladium.
是异常小行星的金属 你觉得它占了徽章的多大比例
The metal from the rogue asteroid. How much would you say of the sigil?
-五分之一  -接近四分之一
-Maybe a fifth of it? -Closer to a quarter.
目前 狄斯比斯人将他们十分之一的矿石 作为宗教税提供给我们
Currently, the Thespins tithe 10% of the mined ore to us.
这是他们用低调的方式表示
This is their way of quietly saying
如果我们站在他们那边 他们愿意将比例提高到25%
they'll go all the way to 25% if we side with them.
这里完全没有金属 连箭头都没有
There's no metal here at all. Not even in the arrow tips.
没错 为什么
That's right. Why?
安纳克里昂人需要钯
The Anacreons need palladium.
他们没有任何钯
They have none.
就像狩猎歌一样 和狩猎完全无关
It's like the hunting song. It's not at all about hunting.
艺术不过是听起来更优美的政治
Art is simply politics' sweeter tongue.
外围星域的风俗也许显得奇怪
The customs of the Outer Reach may seem idiosyncratic.
但我们对于细节的一丝不苟 是我们维系和平的方式
But our attention to detail is how we maintain the peace.
如果人们不守规矩 我们就用武力镇压
And if the people step out of line, we hit them with a big stick.
谢谢
Thank you.
谢顿和那女孩
Seldon and the girl.
在动用武力上不用顾虑太多
Don't overthink the stick.
先知教堂 我们有时间去吗
The Seer church. Do we have time?
有
Yeah.
她可以坐下 他站着
She can sit. He will stand.
但他必须解除武器
But he will need to disarm.
异教徒和我将进行对话
The heretic and I will talk.
觉醒之际
Upon awakening…
我们说出言语
We speak the words.
言语让我们被看见
And the words make us seen.
你知道我是谁吗
Do you know who I am?
我知道她把脸上的沉睡者之语除去了
I know that she has torn the Sleeper's words from her face
因此不能被上帝所看见
and can't be seen by God.
但你知道我是谁吗
But do you know who I am?
她解开了一个最古老的谜语
She has solved one of life's ancient puzzles
在解开谜语的过程中令生命的价值贬值
and cheapened the worth of life in the solving.
我当然知道
Of course I know.
在辛纳克斯 她几乎和她信奉的新神 谢顿一样出名
On Synnax, she is almost as famous as her new god, Seldon.
-他不是神 -对 他不是
-He's not a god. -No, he is not.
他将像所有与他一样的人那样死去 上帝看不见的人
He will die as all men like him die, unseen by God.
他的信徒也一样 她也一样
As will his followers. As will she.
盖尔多尼克 我只会说一次
Gaal Dornick. I'll say this once,
因为我是这个被抛弃的世界里 最高位、也是唯一的先知祭司
because I am the highest-ranking and only Seer priest on this forsaken world.
如果你陷入困境 我能帮助你
If you are in trouble, I can help you.
这是你想要的吗
Is that what you want?
需要我留下吗
You want me to stay?
那样他们就不会逮捕我吗
Will that stop them from arresting me?
不是
No.
我一个人没事的
I'll be all right.
-回头见 -会吗
-I'll see you. -Will you?
当然
Of course.
有些人想在走前再祈祷一次
Some like to pray one last time.
你这么做了吗
Did you?
没有
No.
你觉得她怎么样
What did you make of her?
他们还没找上她
They haven't gotten to her yet.
暂时还没
Yet.
你觉得她怎么样
What do you make of her?
她是靠自己解开亚布拉克萨斯猜想的 这点我很肯定
She solved Abraxas on her own. I'm sure of that.
至于另一个问题嘛 我们以后会知道
As for the other question, well, we shall see.
我是楼斯艾法金
My name's Lors Avakim.
是哈里让我来的
Hari sent me.
他在哪里
Where is he?
被逮捕了 如他所预测的
Arrested. As he predicted.
你们俩都被指控严重叛国罪
You've both been charged with high treason,
密谋危害帝国的稳定
conspiracy to destabilize the Imperium.
这是一场噩梦
This is a nightmare.
哈里希望你知道 将你牵涉进来 他感到非常抱歉
Hari wants you to know how sorry he is for involving you in this.
这不是他的错
It's not his fault.
对吗
Is it?
我们可以无顾忌地说话了
We can speak freely now.
帝国得知哈里的结论后
Once the Imperium learned of Hari's conclusions,
完全没有掩饰他们干扰项目的意图
they made no secret of trying to disrupt the project.
哈里是让我来做饵的吗  因为我可以证明他是错的
Did Hari bring me here as bait? Because I can prove him wrong?
他没有错 多尼克女士
He's not wrong, Ms. Dornick.
但是做饵的猜测是正确的
But yes on the bait part.
你还好吗
Are you all right?
钩得很疼 但我努力保持不动
The hook hurts, but I'm trying not to wriggle too much.
全体起立
All rise.
克里昂12世审判庭开庭
The tribunal of Cleon XII is convened.
尊贵的大人 有罪者哈里谢顿博士和盖尔多尼克
Your Exalted, the offenders, Dr. Hari Seldon and Gaal Dornick,
被指控犯下如此严重的罪行 不仅威胁川陀的和平
are accused of crimes so grave that they threaten not just Trantor
也危及整个银河的存亡
but the entire galaxy's existence.
我将证明谢顿博士和他的信众
I will prove that Dr. Seldon and his followers
参与了密谋 目的为摧毁民众对帝国的信心
engaged in a conspiracy designed to destroy the confidence in our empire.
谢顿博士 请起立
Dr. Seldon. Will you rise?
你原本来自赫利肯星 是吗
You hail from the world of Helicon, yes?
是
Yes.
你能陈述你目前在川陀的职位吗
Will you state your current position here on Trantor?
我是斯璀璘大学的概率理论学教授
I'm a professor of probability theory at Streeling University.
具体而言 是心理历史学范畴
Specifically, the area of psychohistory.
请为我们界定一下这个词
Define that for us, please.
心理历史学是一种预测模型
Psychohistory is a predictive model
用于预测大基数人口的行为
designed to forecast the behavior of very large populations.
简单说来 你声称自己能够预测未来
In plainspoken terms, you claim to be able to predict the future?
我无法预知你的晚餐将吃什么
Well, I don't know what you're going to have for dinner,
如果你问的是这个意思
if that's what you're asking.
你明白我问的是什么
You know what I'm asking.
银河帝国中有八万亿人
The Galactic Empire comprises some eight trillion individuals.
你觉得这个基数 大到足以作为预测的样本吗
Would you say that was a large enough sample to make a prediction?
是的
It is.
对于这个样本 你作出了预测吗
And do you have a prediction for that particular sample?
是的
I do.
请说吧
Indulge us.
川陀和银河帝国将在五个世纪内化为废墟
Trantor and the Galactic Empire will lie in ruins within five centuries.
肃静 各位
Silence, brethren.
假定你的说法正确 你能证明它是真的吗
Accepting your statement for the moment, can you prove it's true?
只能向另一位熟悉序数分析的数学家证明
Only to another mathematician conversant in ordinal analysis.
真省事
How convenient.
你的真理如此晦涩 以至于几乎所有民众都无法理解
Your truths are so esoteric they escape the grasp of nearly every citizen.
那不是我的真理 是科学的真理
They're not my truths. They belong to science.
帝国的历史长达一万两千年 博士
The Imperium is 12,000 years old, Doctor.
我们真的能相信 它会在短短500年内消失
Are we really to believe that it could be gone in just 500?
-也许更快 -更快
-Maybe quicker. -Quicker?
腐朽的树干看上去茁壮 但一场风暴就能让它断为两截
A rotten tree trunk appears strong until the storm breaks it in two.
考虑到近期外围星域的纷乱
Consider recent events in the Outer Reach.
我们来这里不是要考虑其他…
We're not here to consider any other--
但是你们必须考虑
But you must!
帝国将灭亡
The Empire will fall.
社会将失序
Order will vanish.
星际战争将无穷无尽
Interstellar wars will be endless.
无数世界化为辐射尘埃
Ten thousand worlds reduced to radioactive cinders.
我们做的一切都无法避免它的到来
Nothing we do can prevent this.
这个…蛮荒时期
This… period of barbarism.
你认为它将维持多久
How long do you claim it will last?
三万年 律师
Thirty thousand years, Advocate.
我谨此呈报法庭 谢顿博士所谓的“预测”
I submit to the court that Dr. Seldon's "predictions"
事实上是为了摧毁公众的信念
are actually intended to destroy public confidence.
我不是革命分子
I'm not a revolutionary.
那你是什么
Well, then what are you?
你已经说了未来无法改变
You've already said the future cannot be changed.
所以你究竟是为了什么目的 进行这个项目
So what exactly is the purpose of your project?
我想降低这场毁灭的破坏力
I'm trying to soften the fall.
毁灭无可避免
It cannot be prevented,
我们将受到一次又一次大事件的冲击
this mass of events rushing to meet us.
但我们可以缩短灭亡后黑暗纪元的长度
But we can shorten the dark ages that follow.
缩短多少
How much?
如果我们采纳你的计划 能缩短多少
If we embrace your plan, how much?
我们应该会面临一千年的黑暗 律师
We should be in the dark for a thousand years, Advocate.
如果是这样 那我们应感谢诸神
And if that is all, we should thank the gods for it.
其实我不叫杰瑞尔
My name's not really Jerril.
但你可以继续这么叫我
But you can keep calling me that.
我们已经观察你一段时间了
We've been watching you for some time.
其实从你解开 亚布拉克萨斯猜想那刻起就开始了
From the moment you solved the Abraxas Conjecture, in fact.
我给你带了一份礼物
I brought you a gift.
他称之为元光体 很美吧
He calls it the Prime Radiant. It's beautiful, isn't it?
他说里面包含他对帝国的所有预测
He claims it contains all of his predictions concerning the Empire,
以数学等式的形式表现出来
expressed as a mathematical equation.
他允许你查看吗
Did he allow you to examine it?
没有
No.
你不觉得那很奇怪
Now, don't you think that's curious?
他创造了一个深奥的理论 整个银河都没有人能理解
He devises a theory so opaque that no one in the galaxy can understand it,
当他找到一个能理解的人时
and when he finds an individual who can,
却不允许她一探究竟
he doesn't allow her a look behind the curtain.
为什么
Why?
因为历史上充满江湖骗子和虚假先知
Because history is littered with charlatans and false messiahs.
如果他说的是真的呢  如果心理历史学是真的呢
What if he's telling the truth? What if psychohistory is real?
如果他的等式有错
If his equations are flawed,
在道德上 你有义务揭露错误
you have a moral obligation to expose them.
如果等式正确呢
And if they hold true?
否认它的真实性 然后回家
Disavow them and go home.
我向你保证 大帝一定会找到途径 向你表达他的感谢之情
And I promise you, Empire will find a way to express his gratitude.
我就长话短说吧 盖尔
I'll make the calculus simple for you, Gaal.
如果你说哈里是骗子 他会死
If you say Hari's a liar, he dies.
如果你不这么说 你会死
If you don't, you die.
所以我们就采用鸵鸟政策
So, we should just all bury our heads in the sand then?
如果他的公式正确
If his equations hold true,
那么大帝会以我们一直以来的方式 着手解决问题
then Empire will set about solving the problem as we always have,
而不必惊吓到数万亿人
without terrifying trillions of people.
我应该信任你这个间谍的话
And I should believe in you, a spy?
你应该信任建筑起川陀的头脑
You should believe in the minds that built Trantor,
他们建造了跃迁驱动器、星桥
built the jumpdrive, that built the Star Bridge.
在我们那里 这样的人叫科学家 而不是政客
Where I come from, they call those scientists, not politicians.
我知道你来自哪里 盖尔
I know where you come from, Gaal.
这样的人叫异教徒 全被溺死
They were called heretics and drowned.
我也知道跃迁舰上发生了什么
And I also know what happened on the jumpship.
在跃迁期间…
During the jump…
你是清醒的
you were awake.
你醒着
You were aware.
-你为什么要对我说谎  -不知道
-Why did you lie to me about it? -I don't know.
我害怕
It scares me.
怕什么
What does?
怕自己与众不同
Being different.
每个人都是不同的 多尼克女士
We're all different, Ms. Dornick.
我的姐姐长到七岁才开口说话
My sister didn't speak until she was seven.
而且只会说名词
And even then, just nouns.
但你不一样
But you're something else.
如果你不知道自己哪里不一样 我希望你尽快找到答案
And if you don't know what it is, I urge you to figure it out
趁其他人还没发现它 并以此作为攻击你的武器
before someone else does and uses it against you.
你声称你的计划能够缓解即将来临的黑暗
You claim your plan can reduce the coming darkness.
怎么做到
How?
传言古人曾建造一个智库 存放全世界的知识
The ancients are rumored to have built a repository for the world's wisdom.
传说那个智库已被燃烧成灰烬
According to myth, it burned down.
我所建议的方式是非集中式的
I'm proposing something less centralized.
《银河百科全书》
An Encyclopedia Galactica.
灭亡后 文明从灰烬中重生
After the fall, as civilization climbs from the ashes,
未来的世世代代将在此之上重建文明
the coming generations will have something to build upon,
一个基地
a foundation.
他们不需要从零开始 知识已经存在
They won't have to reinvent the wheel. The knowledge will already exist.
但我们需要拯救的不仅仅是知识
But it isn't just knowledge we'd be saving,
而是人类的故事
but humanity's story.
我们的故事
Our story.
川陀已经有一座帝国图书馆了
Trantor already has an imperial library.
还能矗立多久呢
For how long?
这番言论确实触及问题的关键
Now, that statement does bring us to the heart of the matter.
你说你可以向熟悉序数分析的人 证明你的理论
You said you could prove your theorem to someone conversant in ordinal analysis.
盖尔多尼克 请起立
Gaal Dornick, please rise.
请你走到审判台前
Approach the dais, if you would.
你来自辛纳克斯 是吗  我们应该说明这点
You're from Synnax, correct? We should say that.
是的
I am.
你移除了你的祷告石
You've had your prayer stones removed.
你的外表看起来几乎和我们一样
You almost look like one of us.
据我了解 在你的世界 移除祷告石
My understanding of your world is that to remove the prayer stones
意味着与先知教堂决裂
is to break with the Seer Church.
是吗
Is that right?
对 教会的教义是这样
That is church doctrine, yes.
请告诉我 他们仍在杀害 科学家和数学家吗
Tell me, are they still killing scientists and mathematicians?
如果你说的是大杀戮 那…
If you're talking about the Purge, then…
教会用的词是“净化” 尊贵的大人
The church's term is "the Cleanse," Your Exalteds.
根据教会教义 是什么时候开始
When was it, according to church doctrine,
学习数学不再被视为异端分子
that it stopped being heresy to study math?
至今都是这样
It never stopped.
但你却解开了亚布拉克萨斯猜想
And yet you solved the Abraxas Conjecture.
是的
Yes.
在一个人们烧毁大学的世界
On a world where they burned the universities down.
你在那里一定感到很孤独
You must have been lonely there.
我能想象到被哈里谢顿博士认可 是什么感觉
I can imagine how it must have felt to be recognized by Dr. Hari Seldon.
拥有工作的机会 自我价值被认可
To be given a job. To be valued.
你想知道什么
What do you want to know?
我想知道你是否能做到…
I want to know if there is any possible way…
对哈里谢顿保持客观的态度
you can be objective about Hari Seldon.
不知道 也许我做不到
I don't know. Maybe I can't.
也许他带我来就是因为这个原因
Maybe that's why he brought me here.
昨晚你有一个机会
Last night you were given a chance
评估谢顿博士的理论是否准确
to assess the accuracy of Dr. Seldon's claims.
你有结论了吗
Did you arrive at a conclusion?
有
Yes.
是什么
And?
谢顿博士的预测…
Dr. Seldon's calculations…
是正确的
are correct.
帝国将灭亡
The Empire is dying.
杀了他们
Kill them.
结束这一切
End this.
哈里 看天空
Hari, the sky.
星桥那边不太对劲
Something's wrong with the Star Bridge.
请心怀尊敬 享受和平
Please respect and enjoy the peace.
返回母星时间
Expected return to home planet?
三天后
Three days.
-请心怀尊敬 享受和平 -谢谢
-Please respect and enjoy the peace. -Thank you.
本车厢即将开始沿着轨道下降
This car will commence its descent down the stalk momentarily.
您可能会有颠簸感
You may feel a jolt.
请在开始下降前安坐
Please secure yourself before commencing descent.
连接川陀站的索道像绞刑具一样缠绕星球
The tether wrapped around the planet like a garrote.
嵌入地表以下50层
It cut 50 levels down.
-大帝 -闭嘴
-Emperor-- -Shut up!
据说在爆炸前有人听到安纳克里昂 和狄斯比斯的战吼
There are reports of Anacreon and Thespin war cries before the explosion.
背叛之歌
Songs of rebellion.
我们绝对没有参与这件事 我们发…
We had no part in this, we--
我们将退回你们的礼物
We will, of course, be returning your gifts.
86963777
86,963,777.
86963791
86,963,791.
你来这里做什么
What are you doing here?
我向委员会提出呈请
I petitioned the committee.
他们说死了一亿人
They're saying a hundred million dead.
外围星域可能反叛了
The Outer Reaches may be in rebellion.
这次袭击改变了一切
The attack's changed everything.
哈里说你死去的概率非零
Hari said there's a nonzero chance you'll die,
但非零仍然是一个数字
but nonzero is still a number.
盖尔 他们会杀死哈里
They're gonna kill Hari, Gaal.
-你不用与他一起死去 -我已经说了他的预测是正确的
-You don't have to die with him. -I've already said his math was right.
说你又检查了一次 说你弄错了
Say you looked at it again. Say you were wrong.
你失去信念了
You've lost faith.
抱歉
I'm sorry.
她不需要那个
She doesn't need that.
起来
Get up.
我先说还是你先说
Shall I speak first, or will you?
不必客气 谢顿博士
By all means, Dr. Seldon.
请说
Speak.
你把一切归咎于我们
You hold us responsible.
当然
How could I not?
我的科学研究能够预测社会行为、趋势 无法预测个人行为
My science can predict societal actions. Trends. Not individual ones.
但发生这件事我并不意外
But I'm not surprised it happened.
为什么
Why is that?
你们分身乏术了
You're stretched too thin.
所以外围星域的王国率先袭击
That's why the kingdoms of the Outer Reach struck first.
谁能怪他们呢
And who can blame them?
感知到你们的脆弱后 很快将有其他力量 开始对帝国进行破坏
Sensing vulnerability, soon other players will begin to apply downward pressure.
银河中某个主要的宗教必然会发起煽动
An exhortation from one of the galaxy's major religions is a given.
也可能是川陀本地发起的起义
Or perhaps a homegrown insurrection here on Trantor.
星桥的事 这是谁干的
Star Bridge. Who did this?
我不知道
I don't know.
给我一个原因 说服我不该立即处决你和你的信众
Tell me why I shouldn't kill you and your followers right now.
我的信众与此事无关
My followers aren't responsible!
如果你这么做 你一年内就会死去
If you do, you'll be dead within the year.
天才开口了
The prodigy speaks.
说吧
So speak.
你的手下杰瑞尔 让我检查谢顿博士的计算结果
Your agent Jerril asked me to check Dr. Seldon's work.
我对等式进行了进一步的计算
I went a little farther in the equation.
如果你杀死他 帝国将加速灭亡
If you kill him, the fall accelerates.
这个数据对你们还真有利啊
Well, that's a convenient data point for your side.
只有他能缩短黑暗时期
Only he can shorten the darkness.
杀了他就消灭了希望
Kill him, you kill hope.
没了希望
Kill hope…
他们就会杀了你
they kill you.
真巧啊
What are the odds?
仅有的两个能拯救银河的人 都在这个房间里
The only two people who can save the galaxy are in this room.
而其中一人是错的
And one of them is wrong.
我同意
I agree.
如果灭亡的速度可以加快 那可以减慢吗
If the fall can be accelerated, can it not also be slowed?
可以 减慢几个世纪
Yes. By a few centuries.
别对我们有所隐瞒
Don't keep us in the dark.
终止帝国克隆活动
End imperial cloning.
帝国克隆终止了战乱
Imperial cloning stopped the wars.
帝国克隆带来和平
Imperial cloning brought peace.
我们这一脉相承的王朝 已经统治了近四个世纪
Our genetic dynasty has reigned for almost four centuries.
你应该很清楚 年轻的大脑拥有你的智慧 这件事的价值
Surely you can understand the value in a younger mind who shares your intellect.
我能看见差异的价值
Well, I see the value in difference,
新想法的价值
in the new.
你没有任何新的创造
You offer nothing new.
不过是一个更嫩的葡萄
Just a younger grape…
来自同一个葡萄藤
from the same vine,
注定酿成同样的酒
destined for the same old bottle.
你们无法拯救自己
You can't save yourselves…
但你们能拯救功业 传承后世
but you can save your legacy.
你的功业还是我的功业 谢顿博士
Yours or mine, Dr. Seldon?
你用了多久…
How long did it take you…
激活元光体
to trigger the Prime Radiant?
我第二次尝试时成功了
I got it on the second try.
你早知道他们会交给我
You knew they'd offer it to me.
哈里 看着它时 我…
Hari, when I looked at it, I--
我真的以为他们至少会假装一下 让整个过程看起来更公平
I really thought they'd try and make it seem more of a fair fight.
但他们甚至连装都不愿装 对吧
But they didn't bother, did they?
我们尝试了吗
Did we?
钩子那边还疼吗
The hook still hurting you?
赛拉斯用了你之前的话 “我很孤独”
Xylas used the same phrase you did. "I was lonely."
他们在窃听
They were listening.
你知道他们在窃听
And you knew they were listening.
-他们正在窃听 -好吧
-They're listening now. -Fine.
你想让他们听什么
What do you want them to hear?
亚布拉克萨斯猜想是饵 你不是
Abraxas was the bait. Not you.
我只是在他们出手之前先行一步
I just moved before they did.
你的话语权比你意识到的更大 盖尔
You have more agency here, Gaal, than you realize.
大帝决定 处决你们并非最佳选择
The Emperor has determined that your deaths are not the optimal outcome
对于帝国的福祉而言
for the good of the Imperium.
大帝允许你们完善心理历史学研究
You will be allowed to refine your work on psychohistory,
建造你们的基地
to build your Foundation.
但地点不在川陀
But not on Trantor.
而是端点星
Terminus.
座落于外缘区的无人之地
It is uninhabited, sitting in the Periphery,
在银河外围星域的边上
along the galaxy's Outer Reach.
安纳克里昂和狄斯比斯也位于外缘区
Anacreon and Thespis are also in the Periphery.
是 你们将与蛮族王国为邻
Yes, the barbarian kingdoms will be your neighbors.
你们将乘坐慢速舰旅行
You will journey via slow ship.
帝国禁止你们使用跃迁技术
The Empire forbids you access to jumpdrive technology.
你要流放我们
You're exiling us.
在端点星上 你们将不会为川陀制造麻烦
On Terminus, you will not trouble Trantor,
帝国的和平将不受干扰
and there will be no disturbance of the Emperor's peace.
银河众人将知道你们在阻止灭亡
The galaxy will know that you are fighting the fall.
如果心理历史学被证伪
If psychohistory proves fraudulent,
你们的基地将衰败和消失
your Foundation will be allowed to wither and vanish.
如果成功
And if it's successful,
你会将其合并 利用基地巩固你的政权
you'll co-opt it and use it to bolster your regime.
端点星 我从没听过这个地方
Terminus. I've never even heard of it.
那很合理 它在五万光年外
There's no reason you would. It's 50,000 light-years away.
没有跃迁驱动器 去那里需要…
Without a jumpdrive, the journey there--
-878天 -大约
-878 days. -Approximately.
我们不会有事的
We'll be fine.
会遇到困难 这毫无疑问
There'll be hardships, no question.
端点星围绕一颗红矮星转动
Terminus orbits a red dwarf.
那里的季节气候极端 金属和矿物稀缺
Its seasons are extreme. Metal and mineral poor.
你很了解
You know it well.
一开始的计划就是被流放
Exile was always the plan.
端点星一直是最优地点
And Terminus was always the optimal location.
远在外缘区
Out in the Periphery.
拥有帝国支持 不受帝国监控 完美地点
Imperial support without imperial eyes. It's perfect.
还有多少人知道
How many others knew?
只有瑞驰
Only Raych.
你对大帝说的话…
What you said to the Emperor…
你在检查我的计算结果时算到哪一步了
How much farther into my math did you look?
你到底看到了什么
What did you actually see?
-我看不出来 -所以你说了假话
-I couldn't quite figure it. -So, you lied?
我做了一个假设
I hypothesized.
在辛纳克斯 没有人想知道海平面在上升
On Synnax, no one wanted to hear that our seas were rising.
我觉得如果能让人们听进去我的话 我就可能救下他们
I thought if I could make people listen, that I could save them.
改变是令人恐惧的 对于掌权者来说尤其如此
Change is frightening, especially to those in power.
我能感觉到大帝的恐惧
And I could feel the Empire's fear.
但我看进元光体时 我能看见黑暗
When I looked into the Prime Radiant, I could see the darkness.
它一开始让我喘不过气来 难以承受
It took my breath away at first. It was crushing.
然后我往更深的地方看去
But then I looked deeper,
我能看到尽头有一丝光亮
and I could see this tiny sliver of light at the very end of it all.
我意识到他们恐惧的不是灭亡
And I realized it's not the fall they're afraid of.
而是你的计划可能会成功
It's the chance that your plan will actually succeed.
建造比摧毁更需要力量
It takes more power to build than to burn.
我想建造 哈里
And I want to build, Hari.
你会有机会的
You'll get your chance.
这不是基地的第一次危机 也不会是最后一次
This isn't the Foundation's first crisis, and it won't be our last.
我有种感觉 你已经知道下一次危机是什么了
Something tells me you already know what the next crisis will be.
帝王的和平将会持续下去
The Emperor's peace will be maintained.
从辛纳克斯到川陀 现在向端点星进发
From Synnax to Trantor. Now Terminus.
你来这里是希望能拯救你的世界
You came here hoping to save your world.
我请求你把梦想扩大
I'm asking you to dream bigger.
拯救一个世界太少了 何不拯救整个银河
Why stop at one world? Why not save the galaxy?
有道理
Why not indeed.
（端点星）
（35年后）
哈里计划了这一切
Hari had planned for it all,
只有他能预见的事情
things only he saw over the horizon.
（基地）
心理历史学能够预测整个人口的行为
Psychohistory could forecast the behavior of entire populations
精确度极高
with stunning accuracy.
但是个人行为就难以预测了
But, when it came to individuals, things got murkier.
没有人能接近穹窿 只有塞佛哈定是个例外
No one could approach the Vault. No one but an outlier like Salvor Hardin.
我一直在想
And I always wondered…
哈里在制定计划时
when Hari was formulating his plan,
他是否意识到银河的命运 取决于她在里面所发现的东西
did he realize the galaxy's fate would rest on what she found inside?
我认为他知道
I think he did.
我认为那是他最怕的一件事
And I think that's what he feared the most.
（纪念琳达安利维坦）
字幕翻译：易晗